Okay, moving into congenital defects.
These usually arise during embryogenesis,
classically during weeks three to eight.
They're seen in about 1% of live births,
and most of these are sporadic.
They can occur in association with certain circumstances.
That becomes particularly high yield,
but I'll mention those associations as we go forward.
Now, one of the interesting things that can occur
when you get congenital defects
is that you get shunting between the circulations,
whether it be left to right or right to left.
I'll highlight some of these principles as we move forward.
Let's start with the first defect.
So in ventricular septal defect,
you get a defect in the septum
that divides the right and left ventricles.
Of course, the name gives it away, ventricular septal defect.
Important to note,
this is the most common congenital heart defect,
and very high yield is associated with fetal alcohol syndrome.
Now, let's just illustrate the anatomy
to understand the problem.
So here you've got the right atrium and the right ventricle,
and then, of course, you've got the left atrium
and the left ventricle.
And the defect is going to be here
in between the right and left ventricles.
Now, when blood comes from the right atrium
into the right ventricle, there'll be no problem.
From the right ventricle,
it can choose to go into the left ventricle,
which would be a high-pressure circuit,
or stay in the low-pressure circuit,
and so it'll continue on through the low-pressure circuit.
Eventually, blood will return to the left atrium,
and when blood gets to the left atrium,
it'll enter the left ventricle.
From the left ventricle,
it can choose to proceed in the high-pressure circuit
of the systemic circulation
or cross over into the low-pressure circuit
of the pulmonary circulation,
and so you'll get some crossover,
and that crossover is going to result
in a left-to-right shunt,
and that's the key problem in VSD.
Now, if this VSD is small,
then it can be relatively asymptomatic.
However, if the VSD is large,
then large amounts of blood would cross over.
Now, when that large amounts of blood crosses over,
that's going to increase the blood volume
within the pulmonary circuit.
The increase in blood volume within the pulmonary circuit
will eventually result in pulmonary hypertension,
so you'll get a high blood pressure
within the pulmonary circuit,
and eventually what'll happen is that
as blood crosses over the right atrium
into the right ventricle,
there'll be a choice to go into the high-pressure circuit
of the pulmonary circuit because there's hypertension,
or cross back over into the low-pressure circuit,
and eventually the time will come
when it's actually better to cross over
into the relatively lower-pressure systemic circuit.
And so then what will eventually happen
is you'll get reversal of the shunt
so that you now get a right-to-left shunt,
and when you get reversal of the shunt,
you're going to get blue blood,
which is coming from the right side
into the left systemic circuit,
which will then result in cyanosis.
Now, this has been explained in your text
in words as well,
where I say that there's a left-to-right shunt,
the size of the defect determines the extent of shunting
and the age of presentation.
Small defects are asymptomatic,
and large defects can result in Eisenmenger's syndrome.
Now, again, when you get Eisenmenger's syndrome,
there's some important consequences.
For example, the patient will have
right ventricular hypertrophy.
Why?
Because the right ventricle is now pumping
against a much higher pressure.
You can get polycythemia
because as you get deoxygenated blood
coming across into the systemic circuit,
that's then going to result in hypoxemia,
and therefore, you'll get release of erythropoietin,
which will then result in polycythemia.
And finally, you can get clubbing,
and clubbing is a change in the fingernails
due to the cyanosis.
The treatment is surgical closure
for a large defect.
Small defects may close spontaneously.
An atrial septal defect
is when you get a defect in the septa
that divides the left and right atria.
The most common type is called osteum secundum.
However, there's an osteum primum type,
and that's associated with Down syndrome,
which is very high yield.
This results in a left-to-right shunt
with a split S2 on auscultation.
Now, the idea here,
if you go back to the anatomy,
is that you've got the right atrium,
you've got the right ventricle,
the left atrium, and the left ventricle,
and, of course, the defect is here
in between the atria.
Now, what's going to happen
is that blood from the high-pressure circuit
on the left side
will cross over into the lower-pressure circuit
on the right side.
And as that blood crosses over,
you're going to be putting extra volume
onto the right side,
and that extra volume on the right side
will result in a delayed closure
of the pulmonic valve.
Now, that delayed closure of the pulmonary valve
in relation to the aortic valve
will result in a splitting of the S2,
and, of course, the S2
is when the aortic and the pulmonic valve close.
Another interesting finding
of an atrial septal defect
is that if you happen to have a DVT,
for example, down here,
and that DVT were to break off and embolize,
normally it would go up into the right circuit
and eventually make its way into the lung,
resulting in a pulmonary embolus.
However, because in this particular case
you've got an ASD,
it is possible for that embolus
to cross over onto the left side,
and when it crosses over into the left side,
it could then go through the systemic circuit
and lodge, for example, in the brain
or in the distal extremities.
And so that is called a paradoxical embolus
because you get an embolus
that arises from the right side
but then crosses over
to lodge on the left side.
Patent ductus arteriosus arises
when there's failure of the ductus arteriosus
to close, and very high yield
is associated with congenital rubella.
Now, again, if you understand the anatomy,
things become very straightforward.
So let's just briefly illustrate this.
Here's the right atrium,
and then you've got the right ventricle.
Of course, this is all normal,
and you've got the left atrium
and the left ventricle.
Now, coming off the right ventricle
is the pulmonary artery,
and coming off the left ventricle
is going to be the aorta.
Now, immediately coming off the aorta
will be the major branches at the arch,
so we'll make those here.
And then recall that the PDA
connects the pulmonary artery with the aorta
after those major branches come off.
So now what's going to happen in this case
is you're going to go from the right atrium
to the right ventricle,
from the right ventricle to the pulmonary circuit,
and in the pulmonary circuit,
you'll have a choice to cross over
into the high-pressure aorta
or continue down into the pulmonary circuit.
Of course, you'll continue down,
and then eventually blood will come around
from the left atrium to the left ventricle,
from the left ventricle to the aorta,
and eventually that will lead
to the crossing over of blood
from the aorta to the pulmonary circuit.
Now what's going to happen over time
is that as you increase blood volume over here,
you're going to create pulmonary hypertension.
This pulmonary hypertension will eventually result
in reversal of the shunt.
So that blood will eventually cross over this way.
When blood crosses over this way,
you're going to have deoxygenated blood
or blue blood crossing over,
and that blue blood is going to go
into the lower extremities
because here this was going to the upper extremity.
So now you're going to get cyanosis
in a lower extremity later in life,
and that's particularly high yield.
And so again, we say for the PDA
that you're going to have a left to right shunt,
it's asymptomatic at birth,
but it's going to be associated
with a holosystolic machine-like murmur.
If you get Eisenmenger's syndrome,
which would be reversal of the shunt,
that's going to result in lower extremity cyanosis,
and that's because the PDA arises
after the major branches off the aortic arch.
So this is particularly high yield.
The treatment is indomethacin,
and the idea is that indomethacin
decreases prostaglandin E,
and prostaglandin E is what keeps the PDA open.
Prostaglandin E keeps the PDA open.
And so therefore,
removal of prostaglandin E will close the PDA.
The next disorder is tetralogy of flow,
and when you have tetralogy of flow,
there's going to be four problems,
and if you understand the anatomy,
it makes it particularly easy
to understand what's going to happen.
So let's go back to the whiteboard
and simply draw our diagram.
You've got the right atrium,
the right ventricle,
the left atrium,
and the left ventricle.
Now again,
the key problem here
is going to be number one,
you're going to have a stenosis
of the pulmonary outflow tract.
Number two,
there will be a VSD.
Number three,
the aorta will be overriding that VSD.
And number four,
you'll have right ventricular hypertrophy.
So these are some of the key findings.
Now when blood tries to go
from the right atrium
to the right ventricle,
no problem.
From the right ventricle,
because there is a stenosis,
we're going to get shunting
down into the aorta,
which is then going to result
in a right to left shunt.
And so the key finding
is that these will be babies
that will be born,
and they will become cyanotic
because deoxygenated blood
is going into the left
or systemic circuit.
So you get early cyanosis.
Now of course,
the degree of shunting
is all going to be based
on this stenosis.
If this stenosis is really tight,
you'll get more shunting,
and if the stenosis is loose,
you'll get less shunting.
Now one of the interesting things
about these patients
is that they can become
very cyanotic,
especially during exercise.
And so they'll run around,
run around, run around,
and become severely cyanotic.
And then what they'll do
in order to reverse
the cyanotic spell
is that they'll squat down.
When they squat down,
they're basically increasing
the pressure on this side,
and that increased pressure
will decrease the shunt,
sending more blood to the lung.
And when they send more blood
to the lung,
they will then be able to,
again, oxygenate that blood
and become less cyanotic.
And that's an important physiology
to understand in this disorder.
So we say that tetralogy of flow
gives you a right-to-left shunt,
giving early cyanosis,
and the degree of stenosis
determines the extent
of the shunting and cyanosis.
In response to cyanotic spells,
patients will squat.
That will increase
the arterial vascular resistance,
which will decrease the shunt
and send more blood to the lungs.
Now one of the classic findings
will be this boot-shaped heart on X-ray.
So this kind of looks like a little boot,
and that's particularly high yield,
the boot-shaped heart on X-ray.
The next disorder
is transposition of the great vessels.
The anatomy here
is very straightforward,
so let's just explain it.
Right atrium, right ventricle,
left atrium, left ventricle.
Transposition means that the aorta
will come off the right side,
and the pulmonary trunk
will come off the left side.
Now you can imagine,
right atrium to right ventricle to aorta,
the aorta eventually goes
through the systemic circuit
and drains back into the right atrium.
So you're going to create a circle here.
And then left atrium
to left ventricle to pulmonary circuit,
of course the pulmonary circuit
eventually drains into the left atrium.
So you're going to create
a separate circuit here.
So this is going to result
in two independent circuits
that do not mix.
And the only way
that the baby will be able
to survive after birth
is for us to create an opening
between these circuits.
Now one way that you can create
that opening is to maintain the PDA,
and so we can, for example,
give prostaglandin E,
which keeps open the PDA.
So let's go ahead and read now.
Transposition of the great vessels.
So you get the pulmonary artery
arising from the left ventricle,
the aorta from the right ventricle,
as I've already described.
Associated with maternal diabetes.
High yield.
High yield that this is associated
with maternal diabetes.
This is going to present
with early cyanosis,
and that's because the blood
from the right side of the heart
is basically going to go
into the aorta,
and then it's going to go
back into the right side
of the heart
and back into the aorta,
and that'll all be deoxygenated blood
running through the circuit.
Again, we know that
the circuits do not mix.
In order for the baby
to survive after birth,
we're going to need
to create a shunt,
and one way we can do that
is to give prostaglandin E,
which will maintain the PDA
until we can eventually
surgically repair this problem.
Truncus arteriosus
is when you have one large trunk
arising from both ventricles,
and it fails to divide.
So here's the idea.
We've got our standard
right atrium, right ventricle,
left atrium, left ventricle,
and the idea here is that
you've got this large trunk
coming off both ventricles.
Now, of course,
this will eventually divide
into the pulmonary circuit,
and this will eventually divide
into the aorta.
However, what's going to happen
is that the deoxygenated blood
coming from here
is going to mix
with the oxygenated blood
coming here,
so that you're going to send
some deoxygenated blood
down this way,
and it's going to result
in early cyanosis.
And so these patients
present with early cyanosis,
and the reason is
that the deoxygenated blood
from the right ventricle
mixes with the oxygenated blood
from the left ventricle
before those circuits
actually separate.
I've already described that
in the image.
Tricuspid atresia
is when the tricuspid valve
orifice fails to develop,
and again,
the word atresia means
that you fail to form
the lumen of a tube,
and in this particular case,
the tube is the atrium.
Now, basically,
what's going to happen here
is the following.
You've got the right atrium,
right ventricle,
left atrium,
left ventricle,
and of course,
this is where
the tricuspid valve is,
so if this fails to form,
then you're not going
to be sending blood
into the right ventricle.
So, of course,
in response to that,
the right ventricle
is going to become
hypoplastic.
Now, this is classically
associated with an ASD,
so that there would be
an opening here,
and that opening
would allow blood
to cross over.
Now, this baby
is going to present
with early cyanosis,
and that's because
the blood from the right side
is going to move
to the left side,
and so you're going
to get the deoxygenated
blue blood going
into the systemic circuit,
creating early cyanosis.
Coarctation of the aorta
is when you have
narrowing of the aorta,
and it's divided
into two forms,
infantile and adult forms.
Here's a picture
of coarctation,
and you can see here
is the normal aorta
coming off the heart,
and all of a sudden,
there's this narrowing
of the aorta,
and that's called
a coarctation.
Now, in the infantile form,
it's associated
with the PDA,
and the coarctation occurs
just distal
to the aortic arch,
but proximal
to the PDA.
Let's illustrate that.
So here,
it's giving you
standard anatomy.
You've got the right atrium,
the right ventricle,
the left atrium,
and the left ventricle.
Now, basically,
the idea here
is that you've got
the aorta,
and of course,
you've got the major branches
coming off the aorta,
and then you've got a PDA.
So the PDA, of course,
would connect
to the pulmonary circuit.
Now, the coarctation
is going to be here.
So there's going to be
a tightening here.
Now, let's follow blood
in this particular circumstance.
Blood will go
from the right atrium
to the right ventricle,
from the right ventricle
into the pulmonary trunk,
and from the pulmonary trunk,
some of the deoxygenated blood
will actually cross over
and come here
because this block
is making what's beyond it
low pressure.
So because you're going
to have low pressure
behind the block
or beyond the block,
you're going to get blood
crossing over here.
And so you're going
to get some blue
deoxygenated blood
going to the lower extremity,
and these babies
are going to present
with lower extremity cyanosis.
So let's go back
and read what we say
about the infantile form.
It's associated
with a PDA.
I've already shown you that.
You get coarctation
that lies distal to the arch
but proximal to the PDA,
so in between the aortic arch
and its major branches
but before the PDA.
And it presents
with lower extremity cyanosis
and high yield.
It's associated
with Turner syndrome.
Now there is another form
of coarctation
called the adult form.
This is not associated
with the PDA.
You simply just get
this coarctation
that lies distal
to the aortic arch.
And so let's just quickly
illustrate what this
would look like.
And again,
you've got a right atrium
and a right ventricle,
left atrium
and a left ventricle,
and here is the aorta
coming off.
These are the major branches
And then finally,
you've got the coarctation
right here.
Now when you've got
the coarctation here,
right atrium
to right ventricle,
no problem.
You'll come around,
left atrium
to left ventricle,
no problem.
From the left ventricle,
there's going to be
a block here,
so you're going to put
extra blood going this way
because of that block.
So that's going to create
hypertension
in the upper extremities
and it's going to create
hypotension
in the lower extremities.
And so that's the key finding
in the adult form.
Well, let's go ahead
and read what we say
in the text.
We say it presents as
hypertension in the upper extremities
and hypotension with weak pulses
in the lower extremity.
It's classically discovered
in adulthood
and high yield,
it's associated
with a bicuspid aortic valve
and you're going to understand
the consequences
of bicuspid aortic valve
in the next section
when we talk about
valvular disorders.
Now one of the very high yield
associations with this disorder
is that collateral circulation
will develop across
the intercostal arteries
in order to try
to bypass that block
and so that will result
in engorged arteries
causing notching
of the ribs.
Let me illustrate this
because it's
particularly high yield.
So again,
let's go back
and just quickly draw
the simple anatomy.
You're well aware
of the fact
that this is the right atrium,
right ventricle,
left atrium,
and left ventricle
and here of course
is where you've got
your coartation.
Now because there's going
to be increased pressure
over here,
there's going to develop
some collateral circulations
that will come
and try to deliver blood
beyond the block.
One of those collateral
circulations will run
along the surface
of the ribs.
Remember that the
intercostal arteries
run right along
the lower surface
of the ribs.
Now as those become
engorged,
they are going to
compress the surface
of the bone
and they're going to
cause notching
of the surface of the bone
and that's a very
high yield association.
Now here's a picture
of that notching
and you can see
so imagine
the vessels running here
because there's
engorgement of the vessel
it's going to notch
against the ribs
and so you can see
all these notching
of the ribs
where the blood vessels
are running.
Again that's a particularly
high yield association
with the adult form
of coartation
of the aorta
and that concludes
our section
on congenital disorders.